<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Querela geometrica, or, Geometry's complaint of the injuries lately received from Mr. Thomas VVhite in his late tract entituled, Tutela geometrica in the end you have some places at large out of Mr. White's Tutela, and Gulden's Centrobaryca, reprinted, and faithfully translated into English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 90 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56877</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Q162</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21778</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12407266</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12407266</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61432</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56877)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61432)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 289:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Querela geometrica, or, Geometry's complaint of the injuries lately received from Mr. Thomas VVhite in his late tract entituled, Tutela geometrica in the end you have some places at large out of Mr. White's Tutela, and Gulden's Centrobaryca, reprinted, and faithfully translated into English.</title>
                  <author>White, Thomas, 1593-1676. Chrysaspis. English &amp; Latin. Selections.</author>
                  <author>Guldin, Paul, 1577-1643. De centro gravitatis. English &amp; Latin. Selections.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 3-91 p., [3] leaves of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.W.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>White, Thomas, 1593-1676. --  Chrysaspis.</term>
               <term>Guldin, Paul, 1577-1643. --  De centro gravitatis.</term>
               <term>Geometry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-03</date>
            <label>Robyn Anspach</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61432:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61432:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Querela Geometrica: <hi>OR, GEOMETRY'S Complaint Of the Injuries lately received from Mr. THOMAS VVHITE In his late Tract, Entituled,</hi> Tutela Geometrica.</p>
            <p>In the end you have ſome Places at large out of Mr. <hi>White</hi>'s TUTELA, and <hi>Gulden</hi>'s CENTRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BARYCA, Reprinted, and faithfully Tranſlated into Engliſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. W.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:61432:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61432:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Publiſher TO THE <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAving in the following Letter from my Friend, receiv'd a brief account of Mr. <hi>Whites</hi> ſo much fam'd and expected Geometrical Treatiſe, I thought fit to publiſh it for ſatisfaction of many, very deſirous to underſtand the ſucceſs he has had therein.</p>
            <p>Know then, that the Letter conſiſts of two parts. The firſt demonſtrates the many and groſs Errors againſt <hi>Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> committed by Mr. <hi>White</hi> in his <hi>Tutela Geometrica:</hi> which yet he terms his <hi>Chryſaſpis,</hi> or <hi>Golden Shield,</hi> wherewith to defend all his other Works.</p>
            <p>The latter part layes open his moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy proceeding againſt a famous Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematician, by charging him with many and evidently falſe imputations, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to diſgrace him. From all which he is here fully vindicated, as well in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Letter, as in the Additionals.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:61432:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61432:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Querela Geometrica: <hi>OR, Geometry's Complaint Of the Injuries received lately from TUTELA GEOMETRICA. OR, The Copy of a</hi> Miſsive, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have, according to your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, peruſed the ſmall Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ometrical Tract lately pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by Mr. <hi>Thomas White:</hi> whereof accordingly I give you here this brief account. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and occaſion of his preſent Writing, as on this Subject,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61432:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> (having ſcarce hitherto appeared in that kinde) is (as is manifeſt by the Title) to make known to the world the great light he hath received particularly from God in that noble Science of Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; as having never ſtudied it, nor much applied himſelf that way: that thereby other men, conceiving this ſo excellent a Piece muſt needs have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighed to him by particular light from Heaven, may learn thence more to prize and eſteem, then hitherto they have done, his Works already publiſhed. For ſo he tells his Reader in the end of his Preface, that the things he is now to declare, ought to be ſufficient to give eſteem to all his former Labours. For if (ſaith he) they came from the Author, and from that force and vigour of Wit, by which he is able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form many more equal to this,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61432:4"/> then his precedent Works are not to be contemned, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from ſuch a Father, <hi>quia de tali exorta ſunt Patre:</hi> But if it come from Heaven, then much more are his other Works wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy conſideration, to wit, as co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming alſo from Heaven before it.</p>
            <p>Now that they come not from himſelf, he openly avouches, as having never had any Maſter in Geometry, nor much applied himſelf to that Science, or read ſo much as <hi>Euclide.</hi> Yea, he free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledges himſelf ſo little verſed in Geometry, that he plainly affirms, no man will call him a Geometrician, if he be one himſelf: <hi>Intuere me hominem, quem nemo Geometram ſalutet, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dò ipſe ſit.</hi> Whence he concludes, that the things he is now to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver, muſt aſſuredly come from Heaven: <hi>Talis cum ſim, non à me haec habes, ſed ab eo, qui ex legibus
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61432:5"/> Providentiae ſuae, ea gubernationi Eccleſiae ſuae, in hoc rerum ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulo, opportuna &amp; fecit, &amp; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</hi> Being I am ſuch a one; (to wit, ſo little vers'd in Geometry) thou haſt not theſe things from me, but from him, who accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Laws of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, both ſaw and made them fit for the Government of his Church, in this preſent conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture: give him the thanks, &amp;c. Wherefore he exhorts the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, not to neglect his own good, nor contemn a wonder fallen to him from Heaven. <hi>Quod ſupereſt, tibi conſule, &amp; oſtentum a caelo ad te delapſum ne contemnito.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this with ſome other ſuch expreſſions hath Mr. <hi>White</hi> in his Preface; whereby you clearly ſee, how highly he values this his Tract, as fallen from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and accordingly deſires the like eſteem ſhould be framed of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61432:5"/> all his other Works: that ſo his Readers conſidering and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with themſelves, that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible ſo learned and ſubtil a work ſhould come from one that never ſtudyed Geometry, muſt neceſſarily conclude that it came particularly from Heaven: and by conſequence alſo have a better eſteem, then hitherto, of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Labours, as undoubtedly coming from the ſame place.</p>
            <p>This is the aim and drift of Mr. <hi>White</hi> in this his <hi>Tutela;</hi> wherein truly he ſeems, by ſo far expreſſing himſelf, to have given a very great advantage to who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever will impugne his former Writings. For now his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary hath no more to do, but to ſhew (as eaſily he may) that this Geometry never came from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and by conſequence, that neither any of his former Works, (whereof Mr. <hi>White</hi> would have
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61432:6"/> this to be a pattern according to which they are to be meaſured) ever came from thence. This I ſay he will eaſily make manifeſt; for it is impoſſible, that ever ſo weak a piece, as this is, and with ſo many Patent and open er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors againſt Geometry (as we ſhall preſently ſee) ſhould ever come from any Geometrician, much leſs from Heaven. Which that it may appear, we will brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly run over the Propoſitions, as they are in the Book, to ſee which of them may deſerve to be thought to have particularly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from Heaven: and then note onely ſome more patent and obvious errors, ſuch as you your ſelf may eaſily conceive: by which you may gueſs at the reſt, and what can be here expected.</p>
            <p>His Treatiſe then contains in all thirteen Propoſitions; of which the two firſt onely expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61432:6"/> the tearms he is to uſe. The two next are taken out of his Brother, Mr.<hi>Richard Whites</hi> Book called <hi>Hemiſphaerium diſſectum,</hi> as he alſo acknowledges; ſo that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is, that theſe firſt four came not from Heaven. The five fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing aim at the <hi>Quadratura Circuli,</hi> but perform no more then a hypothetical, or conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Quadrature: that is, if ſuch or ſuch a proportion were known, it were poſſible to ſquare a circle; but of ſuch Quadratures as theſe, we have enough alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and books are every where full of them. For the reſt, I finde nothing in theſe propoſitions truly demonſtrated, that may not be found in other Authors: ſo that in theſe nine firſt Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, we have nothing that may be thought a wonder fallen from Heaven, as was promiſed.</p>
            <figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:61432:7"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Of this <hi>Guldens</hi> recalling Mr. <hi>White</hi> (as himſelf teſtifies) was by ſome friends informed; but not being able, as it ſeems, to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine <hi>Guldens</hi> calculation, nor to ſee the force of it, he preſumed to print the ſaid Demonſtration, as his own, and to maintain it to be good, and evident, and <hi>Guldens</hi> calculation, or retractation, to be manifeſtly falſe, as we ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſee.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:61432:9"/>
            <p> This Demonſtration I ſay, Mr. <hi>White</hi> let paſs to the print; yet conceiving, as it ſeems, that people would ſtill think it to be taken out of <hi>Gulden,</hi> it being the very ſame with his, he thought good to joyn thereto another of his own, demonſtrating the ſame aſſertion, in a different way from the former; which he performs in the tenth and eleventh Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions. And certain it is, that this Demonſtration is wholly his own, that is, that it neither came from Heaven, nor from any other Geometrician; it being impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that ſo many and patent er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors ſhould come from any that ever ſtudyed Geometry, or read ſo much as <hi>Euclide;</hi> or even knew but how to reſolve a plain Triangle.</p>
            <p>For in the tenth Propoſition he affirms and pretends to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, firſt, that if in a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61432:9"/> Spiral line of the firſt revolution, be inſcribed a Polygone with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual angles, (as in the adjoyned Diagram, you ſee here inſcribed the Polygone EABCMGHID, with eight equal angles) that then the ſides of the ſaid Polygone ſhall equally exceed each other: that is, as much as DI exceeds IH, ſo much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely ſhall IH exceed HG, and HG exceed GM; and ſo of the reſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he affirms this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon exceſs to be equal to the leaſt ſide of all; <hi>viz.</hi> to the ſide EA. Theſe two Aſſertions he puts in the Title of the ſaid tenth Prop. which is this, <hi>Latera Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goni inſcripti ſpirali per aequales angulos exuperant ſeſe invicem per exceſſus minimo lateri aequales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly he likewiſe affirms, that having let down from the points I, H, G, M, &amp;c. Perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculars
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61432:10"/> to the oppoſite Semidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ameters, (as here you ſee let down the Perpendiculars IK, HF, GL, &amp;c.) that then the parts of the ſaid Semidiameters, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted between the Perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars and the Spiral, that is, the parts KD, IF, GL, and ſo of the reſt, ſhall be equall. This third he inferres (though falſely, as preſently we ſhall ſee) about the middle of the ſaid tenth Prop. in theſe words, <hi>Aequales itaque ſunt rectae</hi> KD, IF, &amp; HL. all which three Aſſertions are evidently falſe, as I ſhall briefly ſhew.</p>
            <p>For if we put the Semidiame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ED (which according to the conſtruction of the Spiral, is here ſuppoſed to be divided into eight equal parts) to contain 800 equal parts; the next EI will contain 700: and EH will have 600, and EG 500, and ſo forward:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61432:10"/> So that the firſt EA will have 100, and EB 200, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Whereby we have now in every Triangle EDI, EIH, EHG, &amp;c. two ſides known, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the angle compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended.</p>
            <p>For example, in the Triangle EDI, we have the ſide ED 800, and E I 700, together with the comprehended angle DEI of 45 degrees. So likewiſe in the Triangle EIH, we have E I 700, EH 600, and the angle IEH 45 degrees as before; and ſo of all the reſt. Which being known, we may preſently by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving the ſaid Triangles, finde the two laſt ſides of the inſcribed Polygone, to wit DI, and IH, to contain the one 581, and the other 505, whoſe difference or exceſs is 76. But if in the ſame manner we reſolve the firſt Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle EAB, we ſhall finde the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61432:11"/> ſecond ſide AB to be onely 147; from whence being taken the firſt ſide EA 100, ſhews the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſide to be onely 47. And ſo in like manner will the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the ſecond and third, AB and BC be onely 65. Now theſe three differences or exceſſes, 76, 47, and 65, are far from being equal, as Mr. <hi>White</hi> would have them. Wherefore in this he muſt needs confeſs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf quite miſtaken, and his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration thereof to be falſe.</p>
            <p>Neither is his errour leſs noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in affirming the ſaid exceſs, (which he alſo falſely ſuppoſes to be common to all) to be equal to the leaſt ſide, that is, to the ſide EA: for EA being 100, is bigger then any of them all, as we have ſeen. Yea, he is ſo inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable in this, that his very eyes might have diſcovered the error.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:61432:11"/>
            <p> His third Aſſertion is alſo as falſe and unexcuſable, to wit, that the lines KD, FI, LH, &amp;c. are all equal. For reſolving the Triangles EIK, EHF, and EGL (in which you have a ſide with all the Angels) you will finde EK 495. EF 424. and EL 353 which being reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively ſubſtracted from ED 800 EI 700. and EH 600, leave KD 305, FI 276, and LH 247. which three numbers are alſo far (as you ſee) from being equal, as Mr. <hi>White</hi> pretends to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonſtrated. Wherefore we muſt needs here conclude, that ſuch Demonſtrations as theſe never came from Heaven, as Mr. <hi>White</hi> perſwades himſelf, and would have us believe. And <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruly whoſoever reads this his tenth Prop. will clearly ſee his want of Principles, and that he was fallen upon a buſineſs he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61432:12"/> not: wherein he was ſo puzzelled, that he quite forgot what he had ſaid he would prove, to wit, that the ſaid com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon exceſs was equal to the leaſt ſide: for of this, after he had put it in the title, he makes no more mention, nor once goes about to prove it.</p>
            <p>Now out of ſo weak and falſe a ground as this of the tenth Prop. he demonſtrates in the eleventh (at leaſt he thinks ſo) that the Spiral line EABCMGHID, is equal to the half circumference DQR: but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain performs it ſo unskilfully, that although the ground now laid in the tenth were true, yet follows not his intent. For by ſhewing onely that it is not big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, he inferrs it to be equal; which is no conſequence, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Antecedent were true: but both the one and the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61432:12"/> other are falſe, as we ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſee.</p>
            <p>Now after ſo weak and falſe a Demonſtration, by which he thinks he hath concluded the ſaid Spiral and half circumference to be equal, he proceeds in the twelfth Prop. to refute <hi>Gulden;</hi> who recalling (as was ſaid) this very Demonſtration, (which now Mr. <hi>White</hi> pretends to be his own, and maintains to be good) clearly ſhews, that not onely the Spiral it ſelf is bigger then the ſaid half circumference; but alſo an inſcribed Polygone, for example of twelve equal an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles, is conſiderably bigger.</p>
            <figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:61432:13"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding this falſe ſuppoſition, he goes forward to demonſtrate againſt <hi>Gulden,</hi> that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61432:15"/> the ſides of ſuch a Polygone ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded together are leſs then the half circumference; which he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms ſo confuſedly, and unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, that it is impoſſible to infer any thing to his purpoſe out of ſuch a diſcourſe. But be the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe what it will, at laſt he ſtrongly concludes againſt <hi>Gul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> that the ſides of the ſaid Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygone are leſs then the half cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference.</p>
            <p>But this his concluſion is moſt falſe, as <hi>Gulden</hi> hath evidently ſhewn, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>prop.</hi> 1. and may be ſo apprehended by any man that knows but how to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve a plain Triangle. For by finding every of the twelve ſides of the Polygone in ſuch manner, as we now found the twelfth or longeſt ſide EC to be 6031. we ſhall have all their numbers, as appears in the here adjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61432:16"/> Table;
<table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>6031</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>5520</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>5011</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>4505</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>4001</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>3501</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>3006</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>2522</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>2053</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>1614</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>1239</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>1000</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Summa lat</cell>
                     <cell>40003</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Semiperiph</cell>
                     <cell>37715</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Differentia</cell>
                     <cell>2288</cell>
                  </row>
               </table> all which added together, make, as you ſee, 40003. Whereas if according to <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medes,</hi> you number the ſaid half Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ſaid Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midiameter ED 12000 thrice with its ſeventh part, we ſhall finde the ſaid half cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference to contain at moſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly 37715: which is far leſs then 40003. And by conſequence the ſides of a twelve angled Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone inſcribed in a Spiral, are abſolutely longer then half the circumference of the firſt circle, as <hi>Gulden</hi> truly and learnedly ſhews againſt Mr. <hi>Whites</hi> ſo weak
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61432:16"/> a Demonſtration for the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as we have ſeen.</p>
            <p>By theſe diſcoveries of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny undeniable errours in his Ageometricall Demonſtration, one would judge that Mr. <hi>White</hi> had the leaſt reaſon of all others to cenſure any one; yet ſuch is his paſſion, that he falls bitterly upon <hi>Gulden,</hi> cenſures, vilifies, and reviles him inſufferably, calling his Computation unskilfull, and that he hath not a jot of Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick or Geometry in him; terming him one of thoſe half Schollars, who ſtealing divers excellent things out of other Learned mens Writings, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make them ſeem their own. This bitter invective hath Mr. <hi>White</hi> againſt <hi>Gulden,</hi> a man who never had in the leaſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended him, perhaps never heard of him, being dead many years
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61432:16"/> ſince, and ſo not able now to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for himſelf. Take Mr. <hi>Whites</hi> own words at the end of his twelfth Propoſition. <hi>Calculus itaque Guldenianus imperitus eſt, &amp; qualem ab ipſo acceptari (neque enim vel talem ipſe inſtruxit) dece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat: Homine prorſus Amathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tico, ut legenti ipſius ſcripta pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num eſt patere.</hi> And a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having taxed his want of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and candor, he concludes him to be, <hi>Hominem officij Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metricij prorſus ignarum; &amp; ex eo ſemidoctorum genere, qui cum ex magnorum virorum ſcriptis egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia multa depeculati fuerint, ut ſua faciant, additis quibuſdam levibus, juſti voluminis oſtentatione ſe vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go diſcentium oſtentant,</hi> &amp;c. This gall, whileſt Mr. <hi>White</hi> flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed amongſt his admirers with his new Demonſtration, might have affixed ſome ſeeming ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh upon <hi>Gulden,</hi> amongſt ſuch
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61432:17"/> Ageometricians as Mr. <hi>White</hi> is, but now appearing by what is ſaid, to proceed from ſo unskilful a hand, it cannot tend to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of any, ſave the cenſurer, who condemns that which he underſtands not. For certainly no Geometrician would or durſt have ſaid ſo much; the Compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation being performed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the 47. 1. <hi>Euclidis,</hi> by the extraction of the ſquare Root; then which there can be none more exact and manifeſt. As for that he calls him <hi>Semidoctus,</hi> a half Schollar, one utterly void of all Mathematick; that he hath ſtolen out of other mens works; and all this immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after ſo many errors commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by himſelf, he hath put the laſh into the hands of ſuch, who if they pleaſe, will quickly know to uſe it; eſpecially being ſo juſtly provoked by ſeeing one of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61432:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> their own Order ſo wrongfully abuſed; and will not fail to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort upon him all that he impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes upon <hi>Gulden.</hi> And truly who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall read this Geometri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Treatiſe (which Mr. <hi>White</hi> eſteems the maſter-piece of all that ever he hath writ) and <hi>Gul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens</hi> Book called <hi>Centrobaryca,</hi> will finde ſo main a difference, that Mr. <hi>White</hi> without any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, by what appears in his, may be ſcarce thought fit to be <hi>Guldens</hi> Schollar.</p>
            <p>And whereas he calls <hi>Gulden</hi> one of thoſe half Schollars, who ſteal out of other Books, they will eaſily make it appear, that, whatſoever it be of <hi>Gulden,</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is, that Mr. <hi>White</hi> hath ſtolen that Demonſtration out of <hi>Gulden.</hi> For even by his own confeſſion it came not from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; <hi>Non à me haec habes, &amp;c.</hi> and to ſay it came from Heaven,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61432:18"/> were a blaſphemy, it being mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly falſe, as we have ſeen: Wherefore it muſt neceſſarily be concluded, that Mr. <hi>White</hi> took it out of <hi>Gulden,</hi> who printed it many years ago, as a particular invention of his own; neither can any other Authour be cited, who publiſhed it before him.</p>
            <p>Truly a man would think Mr. <hi>White</hi> to have already ſaid more then enough in ſo vilifying, and even trampling upon this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, eſpecially there appearing no cauſe for ſuch bitterneſs. But he is not ſatisfied to have thus diſgraced him, as much as lies in his power, with the note of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the Science he profeſſes; but he falls upon his Moral Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, taxing him of Vanity, want of Humility, Candour, and the like, affirming him <hi>to be ſo vain, that although he thought he had committed an errour,</hi> (to wit, in his
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61432:18"/> Demonſtration of the Spiral) <hi>yet he could by no means be induced to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it, by blotting it out, or candid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to confeſs the ſame, but goes on, framing excuſes, as if in the very errour he had carried himſelf gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantly.</hi> Maſter <hi>Whites</hi> words are theſe in the place now cited: <hi>Et (quod faediſsimum eſt) tantae va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis eſt, ut cum erraviſſe ſe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taverat, neque delendo tegere, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que candidè confiteri ſuſtinuerit; ſed excuſationes texere, quaſi in ipſo errore egregiè ſe geſſerit, oſtentare pergat, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O moſt unworthy and falſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny! when I had read theſe in Mr. <hi>white,</hi> and compared them with what <hi>Gulden</hi> ſayes in recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the ſaid Demonſtration of the Spiral, I was amazed, how Mr. <hi>White</hi> did not even bluſh when he writ ſo foul and evident an untruth. For of all that, which he ſo maliciouſly here imputes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61432:19"/> unto this man, there is not one word to be ſeen in <hi>Gulden,</hi> nor the leaſt ground or ſhadow in his writings; yea, the juſt contrary to what is here ſo ſhamefully avouched, doth manifeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, as any man may ſee in his Book called <hi>Centrobaryca,</hi> cited by Mr. <hi>white.</hi> Where <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting the ſaid Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he plainly tells the occaſion of it; <hi>viz.</hi> that being informed that a certain Mathematician had by Calculation diſcovered an errour in his Demonſtration, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though at firſt it made no great impreſſion in him, for he thought himſelf ſo ſecure, that he hoped ſooner to finde a thouſand errors in that Mathematicians Calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, then one in his own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration: <hi>Mille potius ſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bam me in Calculo hujus examinis, inventurum errores, quàm vel uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum in meis inventis; ſed contra
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61432:19"/> quaſi accidit, &amp;c.</hi> But I found, ſayes he, juſt the contrary. For having examined the ſaid Calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, I clearly ſaw the errour, and was forced to confeſs it, <hi>Victus debui dare manus.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he preſently retracts it, and is ſo far from excuſing the error, or refuſing to confeſs it, or brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging as if he had carried himſelf gallantly therein, (as Mr. <hi>White</hi> moſt falſely and injuriouſly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes upon him) that he plainly and candidly confeſſes it, ſaying, that he had rather follow the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of other worthy Authors, who in like caſe have, to their own praiſe and profit of others, revoked their errours, then of ſuch as had rather accuſe <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medes, Euclide,</hi> yea, Geometry it ſelf, then once acknowledge the errours of which they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced.</p>
            <p>As to that whereof Mr. <hi>White</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:61432:20"/> moſt wrongfully taxes him (in thoſe words <hi>neque delendo tege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re</hi>) for printing the ſaid Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, although he thought it to be falſe, <hi>Gulden</hi> gives there alſo the reaſon, why he printed it: to wit, that others ſeeing how he had erred in a Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, which at firſt ſight ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo currant, might beware of the like fallacy: <hi>Ut ſciant ſibi ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere a ſcopulis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By all which is moſt evident, that it was ignorance, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and neither knowledge, nor reaſon, which extorted theſe ugly cenſures from Mr. <hi>White</hi> againſt <hi>Gulden:</hi> and how far that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor was from that vanity and ſtubbornneſs in maintaining what he had once aſſerted, though he thought it to be falſe, as Mr. <hi>White</hi> would make the world believe. For I dare main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that there is not an Author
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61432:20"/> to be found, who in the like caſe hath carryed himſelf more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly and candidly then this man hath done: as any, who ſhall read the ſaid third <note n="*" place="margin">As you may ſee at the end of this Letter.</note> chapter, will, to <hi>Guldens</hi> praiſe and Mr. <hi>Whites</hi> confuſion, plainly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. And God grant Mr. <hi>White</hi> may but with as much humility recall and acknowledge what he hath written amiſs in matters of more concern, as this man does retract his Mathematical error.</p>
            <p>Wherefore in this ſo much vilifying of <hi>Gulden,</hi> he hath again put the laſh into his adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries hands, who may uſe it at their pleaſure, and make known unto the world, that no man that had any worth in him, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or moral honeſty, would ever ſo unworthily have carried himſelf as Mr. <hi>White</hi> hath in this. Yea, they may, if they pleaſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort all that he ſo wrongfully
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61432:21"/> layes upon <hi>Gulden,</hi> moſt juſtly upon Mr. <hi>white:</hi> making it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that he is rather to be taxed of vanity, as having gotten one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome few Tearms of Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, (and yet more then he knows well how to uſe) would fain have the glory of a Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian. For although with the one hand he ſeems to drive it away, yet with the other he draws it to him, as any man but reading his Preface will clearly ſee. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he tell his Reader, that he is no Geometrician; and that theſe ſo great things (as he fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies them) come not from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf but from God; <hi>Non à me haec habes,</hi> &amp;c. yet he would have him withall to take notice and well underſtand, that he is alſo able even by the force of his natural wit, to perform as great things as theſe are. For ſpeaking of himſelf and what he is to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61432:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> in the ſaid Geometrical Tract, he writes thus: <hi>Author vel ſuâ induſtriâ perfecit quae of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, vel privilegio magnae Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videntiae accepit. Si à ſe, &amp; inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nij eâ virtute, qua plura ejuſmodi conficere in parato habeat, certè is eſt, ut non ſint contemnenda illa cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera, quae in publicum uſum elabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravit,</hi> &amp;c. Whereby you ſee, he plainly tells his Reader, that he hath now already in ſtore di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other things, as good as theſe. <hi>Plura ejuſmodi in parato ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet.</hi> And theſe alſo found out by the vigour and ſtrength of his own wit. <hi>Eâ ingenij virtute, qua,</hi> &amp;c. Yea although he tells his Reader, that he moſt onely thank God for theſe wonderfull things; and that in thanking the Author he ſhall do him injury, and lay a burden on his ſhoulders more then he is able to bear: <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi ſi grataris, injuriarum te poſtulo,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:61432:22"/> quod plus in me oneris aggeras, quam cui ſim ferendo.</hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he plainly ſhews by what you have heard, that he is ready and able to bear more thanks, then I believe his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will give him: eſpecially when he ſhall perceive himſelf deluded in the Preface, with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of wonders from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and when all is done, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing worth the reading.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>White</hi> is not content with ſo much depreſſing this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, but paſſes further, branding him with the badge of an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, or worſe; intimating him to be one of that pernicious Sect of Pedants, who by their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, labour and endeavour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy not onely all humane Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, but even Chriſtian Faith it ſelf, by taking all certainty from them. For giving a reaſon why he ſo much enveighs againſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61432:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> a man wholly unknown to him, he preſently adds, <hi>Quantumvis operae pretium erat, lectorem moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum reddere de exitiali hac ſciolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſecta, quae ſub profeſsione fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultatis garriendi, omnem certitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem, tum è ſcientiis, tum ex fide Chriſtianâ tollere molitur.</hi> Here Mr. <hi>White</hi> ſtops; and truly it was time: for having forgot what he firſt intended, to wit, to draw out a perfect picture of <hi>Gulden,</hi> he hath miſtaken the colours, and goes on drawing forth his own, as any man that ever knew them both, will evidently diſcover.</p>
            <p>Now if you ask me what was the main cauſe, that moved Mr. <hi>White</hi> to this height of paſſion, he himſelf tells you, to wit, that he was forced and compelled to utter thoſe cenſures. And why? Becauſe the ſhadow (as he ſayes) of <hi>Guldens</hi> great Tome did hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Scholars from embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:61432:23"/> the truth (he ſhould have ſaid the <hi>falſity</hi>) he propoſed to them. For ſo he writes in the place before cited. <hi>Haec coactus ſum de homine caeteroqui ignoto prodere, quia umbra Tomi illuſtris, per opinionem conſequam, officiebat veritati, quam ejuſdem ſtudioſis offerebam.</hi> In which words I ſhould rather think Mr. <hi>White</hi> to have wronged his Scholars, in making them ſuch as ſhould be frighted with a ſhadow. But it ſeems more probable, that his Scholars better underſtood the force of <hi>Guldens</hi> Computati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then their Maſter either would or could, and ſaw clearly that it did conclude. Howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is moſt ſtrange, that any wiſe man for ſo frivolous a toy as this, ſhould ſo highly offend both Almighty God and his Neighbour, and ſo evidently expoſe his own reputation to the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:61432:23"/> unavoidable ſtain of a notorious Detractour.</p>
            <p>Truly, as it ſeems to me, in this the particular hand of God ſhews it ſelf, as well for his own good, (if he will make uſe of it) as for the good of others: in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting Mr. <hi>White</hi> ſo to croſs his own deſigns, that whereas he thought in this Tract to advance himſelf and his former writings, in the repute of every one, he ſhould finde the quite contrary. For whereas he thought thereby to have got the name of a great Mathematician, he hath clearly ſhewed that he is none; and that he is indeed onely furniſhed with ſuch general Terms and common Notions in the Mathematicks, as being with confidence and boldneſſe pronounced in the company of ſuch, as do no more thorowly underſtand them then himſelf, are apt to produce in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61432:24"/> their mindes, an opinion, that the pronouncer is certainly a learned man, &amp; underſtands exactly what they hear ſo ſtrongly aſſevered by him: whereas if ſome learned Mathematician ſhould perhaps over hear him he would ſmile to hear ſo much Geometrical Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe. Nay, whereas he aſſured himſelf to conciliate an immove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able authority to all his former Dictates amongſt his admirers, by this unparalleld Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, even ſome of them (as I am certainly informed) have diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the weakneſs of it, and both bluſh to ſee it, and labour to hide it. In like manner, whereas (by vertue of his ſaid <hi>Tutela</hi>) he aimed to be accounted a perſon whom Almighty God particularly deſigned to uſe as his Inſtrument for the governing of his Church in this preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture; and to this effect, to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:61432:24"/> have received great light and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed knowledge from him, as we have heard him ſpeak in his Preface; he hath now given ſuch a Character of himſelf, that it is impoſſible, that any man ſhould be ſo ſimple as to think, that the wiſdom of God would particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly make choice of ſuch an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument for ſo high a Work; to which men of far greater Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Perfection of Vertue then he can with any reaſon or ground be ſuppoſed to have, are wont to be called.</p>
            <p>This unworthy proceeding of Mr. <hi>White</hi> had made me almoſt forget to refute his <hi>Quadratura Circuli,</hi> pretended to be ſhewen in the firſt nine Propoſitions: which I deferred to the laſt, becauſe he in his thirteenth and laſt Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition hath put the laſt hand thereunto, and ſo confirmed as he thinks the ground thereof, that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:61432:25"/> he ſuppoſes it now as evident (to uſe his own phraſe)as that a Boat is a Boat.</p>
            <figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:61432:25"/>
            </figure>
            <list>
               <item>1. EG 500, as being the Sine of the angle EBC 30 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and by conſequence the greater Axis GF is alſo 500.</item>
               <item>2. By the uſual proportion of the Diameter to the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence we ſhall finde the Sector E B F C, being the third part of the whole circle, to contain 10476191/21.</item>
               <item>3. By the Perpendicular EG 500, and the half baſe GB 866, or Sine of 60 degree. We ſhall finde the Triangle EBC to contain 433000: which being ſubtracted from 10476191/21 the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:61432:27"/> whole Sector, leaves 614619<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> for the greater Segment BFCB.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In like manner, if we put AB the Semidiameter of the leſſer Segment BDCB to be 2000, that is, double to EB, we ſhall finde</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. By the 47. 1. <hi>Eucl.</hi> AG 18027/9 <hi>proximè:</hi> which taken from A 2000, leaves 1972/9 for the leſſer Axis GD.</item>
               <item>2. By what is known in the Triangle ABE we ſhall finde the angle BAE, whoſe double ſhews the whole angle of the Sector ABDC, to be 51 degr. 19′ 30″ from whence by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion thereof to 360 degr. is found the Sector ABDC to contain 1792126.</item>
               <item>3. By the Perpendicular AG 18027/9, and the half baſe BG 866, is found the Triangle ABC to contain 15612051/9 which being taken from the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:61432:27"/> whole Sector 1792126, leaves 2309204/9 for the leſſer Segment BDCB.</item>
            </list>
            <p>So that now we have the ſaid Segments and their Axes, all four in numbers, to wit, the greater Axis 500, the leſſer 1972/9 the greater Segment 6146191/21 and the leſſer 2309204/9 which four numbers are by no means pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portional, as they ſhould be, if Mr. <hi>Whites</hi> Demonſtration were true. For by ſaying as 500 to 1972/9 ſo 6146191/21 to a fourth, there will not be found (as was expected) 2309204/9 but another number far bigger, to wit, 2424331/3 the difference being (as you ſee) 115128/9. Which great difference ſhews evidently the falſity of Mr. <hi>Whites</hi> Aſſertion. Yea, if we put the greater Seg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentto want but very little of a Semicircle, for example onely one Minute, or one Second, &amp;c.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:61432:28"/> the errour will be yet more noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and the proof more eaſie. For then the greater Axis will be 1000 <hi>Proximè,</hi> and the greater Segment will be 1571428: the leſſer Axis will be 268: and the leſſer Segment 363238. which four numbers are yet far more diſproportional: for by ſaying as 100 to 268: ſo 1571428 to a fourth, we ſhall finde 411142, which is greater then 363238 by 47904, almoſt an eighth part of the leſſer Segment. So Mr. <hi>Whites</hi> Demonſtration of the <hi>Quadratura</hi> comes to juſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. But this is like the reſt: for with him Demonſtrations are nothing but ſtout and undaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed aſſeverations, proved by a company of Terms (that make a ſhew of learning to the unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) jumbled at a venture toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Some perhaps, to excuſe this
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61432:28"/> ſo groſs an errour of Mr. <hi>Whites,</hi> will ſay, that by <hi>Portiones Circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum</hi> he meant not the Seg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as we have ſaid, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Arches or Circular Lines BFC and BDC. But this explication will not ſuffice: for neither had this been to his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for the <hi>Quadratura:</hi> nor in it ſelf is it true. For neither are theſe Arches proportional to the ſaid Axes; the one BFC being 20955/21 and the other BDC be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 17921/2 which numbers have by no means the ſame proportion that 500 hath to 1972/9 as a blinde man may ſee. Wherefore Mr. <hi>White</hi> muſt be content to lay up this Errour with the reſt.</p>
            <p>And thus much, Honoured Sir, concerning ſuch things as Mr. <hi>White</hi> pretended here to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, but hath not performed. But if you ask me what he hath in this little Treatiſe truly and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:61432:29"/> clearly demonſtrated, I can one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwer, that he hath demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, firſt that he hath a great deal of vanity: ſecondly, that he hath very little or no Geometry: and thirdly, that he hath as little or leſs charity. For the reſt, I have no more to ſay at preſent, but hoping you will rather reflect upon what is here ſaid, then up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the rude and unpoliſht Style by which it is expreſt, I remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:61432:29"/>
            <head>The Publiſher TO THE <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAving Printed the precedent Letter, and underſtanding before the publiſhing of it, that Mr. <hi>Whites Tutela</hi> ſo often mentioned, was ſuppreſt, no more Copyes to be had, whereby the Reader might receive ſatisfaction in conferring what is here ſaid, with the Authors own words: I thought good to annex ſuch places, <hi>verbatim</hi> out of Mr. <hi>Whites</hi> Book, as are touched in the ſaid Letter. To which purpoſe I have alſo adjoyned <hi>Guldens</hi> Retracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Spiral, taken out of his Book, <hi>de Centro Gravitatis,</hi> the Book it ſelf being dear, and ſcarce to be got. I have put both theſe, firſt in Latine, as
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:61432:30"/> they were written by the Authours: next in Engliſh, becauſe the precedent Letter mentioning them, is alſo in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh. And firſt I will ſet down Mr. <hi>Whites</hi> Preface to the Reader, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firſt mention made of it in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Letter. Which Preface is to be ſeen in the beginning of the ſaid Book, to which he frames this Title,</p>
            <floatingText type="extract">
               <body>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
                     <head>CHRYSASPIS, Seu Scriptorum ſuorum in Scientiis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurioribus Apologiae vice propalata TUTELA GEOMETRICA Ad Lectorem Cordatum &amp; Serium.</head>
                     <p>ARiſtotelis (dicam, an Naturae?) pomaeria extenderat Digbaeus E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques, coactis in pellucida ſtativa Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae partibus, quas turbidè miſcuerat generationum neceſſitas. Solum, fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datura Subſtructiones, occupaverat quanti ipſa moles, rari denſique ſuprà ſerpentium ludis teſſellata. Proximo ſeſe expoſuit gradu fraterna elemento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:61432:30"/> acies, primis (ut appellant) arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta qualitatibus. Haec obnixis in alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam internecionem frontibus, conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guineo cruore quanti aream, ad inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſtam mixtorum ubertatem per ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirandos &amp; inſcrutabiles plexus ebul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liendam irrigant &amp; faecundant. Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant mixta Phrygionatae ſecundarum qualitatum Texturae; accendebant Actionis &amp; Paſſionis emicantia &amp; hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum contuitum obtundentia lumina. Sed neque Electricorum aſſultus &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultus, neque Magneticorum in Homo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geneo corpore mutabiles quaſi conſultò leges; neque Sympatheticorum ex inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diis doloſa &amp; tenebricoſa è longinquo Sagittatio, origines &amp; ſemitas ſuas à tam acri veſtigatore celare valuêrunt. Quin &amp; ad ſuperiora ſedilia mixtorum capita plantae aſcenderunt, &amp; gradum ad ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malia promoverunt. Hic ſe objecêrunt ſcrutino ſenſus &amp; ſenſuum metae, vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerandi quodammodo naturae limites: &amp; ſuperati ſcrutatoris oculum in arcana Animae, &amp; inviſum orbem trajecêre. Subſtitit in hâc altitudine Digbaeus, materiam &amp; materiatorum univerſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem tanto à ſe intervallo in imum diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, non ſine horrore deſpectans; &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliſſimo
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:61432:31"/> operi, cui de <hi>Immortalitate Animae</hi> nomen fecerat, columnas appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit. Tantus erat Scientiae fulgor, ut lippitudini ſaeculi caecitatem adjiceret, &amp; furebant vanitatis, quae in multiloquio effloreſcit, amatores veritatis imaginem non ſuſtinentes, &amp; potioribus haec ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis adverſari jactiabant.</p>
                     <p>Proptereà neceſſarius erat aliarum Diſciplinarum conſenſus, &amp; rudem ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptaverat ingentis illius opificii Author. Inventus ſum, qui etſi Eloquentiae De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſoris impar &amp; compendio natus, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derem deſideratorum Epitomen aggredi, &amp; contractis, quae fuſius Digbaeus, &amp; pro rerum qualitate diſputaverat; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Metaphyſicâ tum corporum tum incorporeorum delineatione, Inſtitutiones Peripateticas conderem. Adjeci &amp; Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cras, &amp; opuſcula (quamvis nihil meum opuſculi molem excedat) nonnulla Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophica, de Mundo Dialogum, &amp; praefationem ante Latinam Editionem operis Digbaeani. Theologicam quoque Buccinam de Fidei &amp; Theologiae Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>râ; &amp; ejuſdem defenſionem adverſus errorem cujuſdam Regularis de Perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li Infallibilitate Papae. Praeterea de Gratiae cum libertate conſenſu, &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:61432:31"/> Animarum ſtatu ſingula Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tariola. Non mirum, ſi haec duriùs excepta ſint, quam Digbaeani labores. Cum &amp; infaeliciori ſtylo ſint exarata, &amp; iter caecioribus obfeſſum ſcopulis &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis affectuum tempeſtatibus objectum terant. Sed idcircò maximè, quod in omnibus Phyſicam, Metaphyſicam, &amp; ipſam Theologiam, inaudito conamine ad ſeveriores Diſciplinas adjungere, &amp; Architectonicam contignationem perſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctabilem in toto proceſſu, &amp; dictorum conſenſum &amp; conſequentiarum fidem (nihilominus citra rigoris Geometrici oſtentationem) in eas inducere tentave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim. Quare hunc deſiderari ſuſpicatus duos Euclidas, Phyſicum majorem natu, adoleſcentiorem Metaphyſicum effudi, non vanae ſpei futuros vades. Verum enim verò etiam hanc evidentiam obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natâ incredulitate opprimi ſum exper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. Quid ſuper mihi reliqueram? Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineram à Novatoribus fidei poſci mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racula. Sed ad ea quae ſuâ evidentiâ ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilienda erant, flagitare argumenta ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trà vim naturae poſita propudioſum erat: attamen ſi quae in Scientiarum Theſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris admiranda laterent miraculis ſuppa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, non immeritò ad difficiliorum fidem
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:61432:32"/> adhiberi conſentaneum erat. Conjeci itaque oculos in Geometriam, cujus ſi qua dogmata hujuſmodi veneratione conſecrata laterent, ea neque alienis ad famam praeſidiis indigerent, &amp; ſuo mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitis ſigillo fidem conciliarent. Et ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verti reſervata quaedam ab ipſa uſque Diſciplinae infantiâ arcana, quae maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morum ingeniorum labores paſſa in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibiliam tranſiverant claſſem. Pap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus &amp; plerique poſteriores Geometrae tres Problematum ordines declarave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; quorum infimus regulâ &amp; circino perficiebatur; medius corporum ſectili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um vi; ſupremum non niſi fictitiis lineis ſubjiciebant. Et in poſterioribus haec arcana recondiderant. Vieta etiam adjectis argumentis quaedam <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> demonſtraviſſe viſus eſt. Carteſius de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperatam rem agnovit. Plerique pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſito Problemati ſatisfeciſſe ſibi viſi ſunt, ſi ad hoc redegiſſent, ut eo ſoluto monſtrarent aliquod clauſorum iſtiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi eſſe reſeratum. Te teſtem invoco, Maxime Archimedes, in ſecundà ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundi de <hi>Sphaerâ</hi> &amp; <hi>Cylindro,</hi> niſi men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dax imponat memoria, Hinc itaque captandam ſcriptis meis umbram cenſui. Tu modo apud temet in conſilium ſe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:61432:32"/> vocatum hoc penſi habeto. Author vel ſuâ induſtriâ perfecit quae offert, vel privilegio magnae Providentiae accepit. Si à ſe &amp; ingeniieâ virtute, quâ plura ejuſmodi conficere in parato habeat, certè is eſt, ut non ſint contemnenda illa caetera, quae in publicum uſum elaboravit; imo hoc nomine trutinâ acri àigna, quia de tali orta ſunt patre. Sin ab exorti <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> vigilantiâ profectum hoc munus ſuſpicaris, expende quanto fortiùs te ad reliquorum examinationem allegatum comperias. Me aſpicis? Intuere me hominem, quem nemo Geometram ſalutet, modo ipſe ſit. Neque e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim Geometrices plenitudinem vel ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petivi. Prelectorem non audivi; ſtudium non ſum profeſſus; magnorum Authorum nullum perlegi, non ſaltem Euclidem. Aliarum Diſciplinarum ambitio me ſemper traxit &amp; defixit: Geometricorum hunc fructum &amp; ſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi &amp; tuli, ut eorum rigorem ad Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſica traducerem. Caeteroqui oblecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento mihi erant, cum deforet potiorum commoditas. Talis cum ſim, non à me haec habes, ſed ab eo, qui ex legibus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videntiae ſuae ea Gubernationi Eccleſiae ſuae in hoc rerum articulo opportuna &amp;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:61432:33"/> fecit &amp; vidit: Illi accepta refer. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi ſi grataris, injuriarum te poſtulo, quod plus in me oneris aggeras, quam cui ſim ferendo: &amp; in Deum, à quo avertis quale quale à te debetur benignitatis praemium. Quod ſupereſt, tibi conſule, &amp; oſtentum a coelo ad te delapſum ne contemnito.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
                     <head>In Engliſh thus. A GOLDEN SHIELD: OR, <hi>A Geometricall Defence</hi> As an APOLOGY for all his other Writings in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurer Sciences.</head>
                     <byline>By Mr. <hi>Thomas White.</hi>
                     </byline>
                     <p/>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:61432:33"/>
            <p> As for the Preface, the firſt part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of concerns not our preſent purpoſe, as ſpeaking onely of the profound re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearch made into nature by that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Gentleman, Sir <hi>Kenelme Digby,</hi> (whoſe learning and reſpects to Mr. <hi>White</hi> would never certainly have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered this Geometrical Treatiſe to paſs abroad, had he ſeen it before it was publiſhed) I ſhall onely Engliſh the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, which Mr. <hi>White</hi> falls upon by occaſion of an objection that ſome things touched in Sir <hi>Kenelmes</hi> Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy ſeemed not fully agreeable to Sciences of higher conſequence. The refutation of which objection Mr. <hi>White</hi> undertook, and ſo gives a brief account of ſuch writings as he had pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed to that effect: and comes at laſt to this preſent <hi>Tutela</hi> which he is about to publiſh, intending it as a defence of all he hath hitherto writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and whereof he ſpeaks to his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in theſe words, <hi>Tu modo apud te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi> &amp;c. as we ſaw juſt now.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="extract">
               <body>
                  <head>In Engliſh thus.</head>
                  <p>TAke gentle Reader this into thy ſerious conſideration, either the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:61432:34"/> Author (meaning himſelf) hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the things he here preſents thee with, by his own Induſtry, or by Gods peculiar Providence. If they be the fruits of his own induſtry, and proceed from that vigour of wit, by which he is alſo ready to perform ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the like: certainly he is a perſon whoſe other writings formerly pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed for the common good, ought not to be contemned. Yea, for this very reaſon, they deſerve a profound conſideration, as proceeding from ſuch a Father.</p>
                  <p>But in caſe thou conſider them as coming from the Almighty, then think with thy ſelf; how much great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er thy obligation is to examine the reſt of his Works. Lookeſt thou upon me? Behold the man, whom no man will call a Geometrician if he be one himſelf. Neither did I ever deſire to compleat my ſelf in that faculty; I was never taught it, nor did I ever pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to ſtudy it. I never read over any chief Author in that Science, no not ſo much as <hi>Euclide;</hi> but was alwayes delighted with other ſtudies. From Geometry I both expected and attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:61432:34"/> ſufficient for transferring its vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous proceedings to the Metaphyſick. Otherwiſe it was onely my recreation when I wanted better employment. Since therefore I am ſuch, thou haſt not theſe things from me, but from him, who in his Divine providence, both ſaw and fitted them for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of his Church in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent conjuncture. Give him the thanks; for if thou apply them to me, I ſhall expoſtulate the injury done me in laying a greater weight upon me then I am able to bear; and thou wilt loſe the reward thou ſhouldeſt receive from God. It remains that thou neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect not thy own good, nor contemn a wonder come down to thee from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Thus Mr. <hi>White</hi> in his Preface. By all which, and by the Title of his Book, he plainly ſhews, that according to the clearneſs and ſolidity of the following Demonſtrations in Geometry, men muſt take the juſt meaſure of the ſolidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſtrength of his other Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Philoſophy and Divinity. And thus much for thoſe places of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face mentioned in the precedent Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:61432:35"/> I will now ſet down thoſe that concern the diſpute between Mr. <hi>White</hi> and <hi>Gulden,</hi> which are onely two; the former is in <hi>Nota ſecunda</hi> before the tenth Propoſition: the latter in <hi>Nota Quarta</hi> at the end of the twelfth.</p>
            <floatingText type="extract">
               <body>
                  <div type="part">
                     <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
                        <head>Ex Tutela Geometrica ante Prop. 10. Nota Secunda.</head>
                        <p>Finieram, &amp; regulam cum circino conſecraturiebam; cum ab amicis mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus ſum, quam in Exercitatione Geometrica exhibueram ſpiralis ad Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripheriam Circuli aequationem, à magni nomin<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> Mathematico, &amp; prius excogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatam, &amp; eàdem demonſtratione con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatam, &amp; poſterioribus conſiliis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudiatam fuiſſe, &amp; oppoſitâ demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione reprobatam. Conſcius eram, non indiligentèr apodixi meae invigilaviſſe. Terruit tamen hominem (cui omnia alia prae Matheſs praehabita fuerant) tot no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis veritatis impreſſus rumor. Tollo de Tabula manum, &amp; cum typis manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſſem, quae ſunt praemiſſa, caeter a uſque ad examinationem hujus improperii ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinenda decrevi.</p>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:61432:35"/>
                        <p> Author oppoſitionis erat quidam <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Guldenus,</hi> ex Societate Jeſu, editor juſti voluminis, quod pro Geometrico ſuppoſitum <hi>Centrobaryca</hi> appellavit. Quid agerem? ubi degebam, opus illud non apparebat, &amp; negotium quod illic gerebam, ad umbilicum perductum erat, &amp; jam egelidum ver monebat aeſtivam ſedem Ciconiarum monitu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> veſtigare. Contuli me itaque <hi>Lugdunum Batavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> &amp; gratiâ clariff. Mathematum ibidem Profeſſoris Examinationem Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blematis mei aggredior. Primò ipſam reviſi; apparuit conſtantiſſima: ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam tibi ſic accenſeo, &amp;.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
                        <head>In Engliſh thus.</head>
                        <p>I Had even now ended, and began to lay my Rule and Compaſs aſide, when I was admoniſhed by my friends, that the equation of a Spiral to the circumference of a Circle, which I had demonſtrated in my <hi>Exercitatione Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrica,</hi> had been found out before and confirmed with the ſame Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by a famous Mathematician: who afterwards retracted it, and by a contrary Demonſtration, ſhewed it to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:61432:36"/> be falſe. I was conſcious to my ſelf that I had not ſlightly examined my Demonſtration: nevertheleſs a rumor with ſo many marks of truth ſomewhat frighted me, being a man that eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all other learning before the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematical. I preſently made a ſtop, and having printed the precedent part <hi>de Quadratura,</hi> I deferred the reſt, till I had examined this reproach.</p>
                        <p>The retracting Author was one <hi>Paul Gulden</hi> of the Society of Jeſus, who had printed a compleat Volume, which he pretending to be a Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricall Work, called it <hi>Centrobaryca,</hi> What ſhould I do? Where I then lived. this Book was not to be had, and my work in hand was even now finiſhed. Beſides the Spring drawing on, did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite me by the crying of the Storks, to ſeek my Summer habitation. I went therefore to <hi>Leyden</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> and with the favour of the moſt famous Profeſſor of Mathematicks there, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to examine my Probleme; I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed it, and found it moſt ſolid, Take here the ſumme thereof, &amp;c.</p>
                        <p>This is Mr. <hi>Whites</hi> relation of the beginning of the Diſpute between
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:61432:36"/> him and <hi>Gulden,</hi> handſomely, as you ſee, contrived, that he may not ſeem to have ſtollen the ſaid Demonſtration out of <hi>Gulden,</hi> but to have fallen upon it himſelf, or had it from Heaven. Yet all this will not ſerve his turn, but ſtill the Reader will imagine thoſe words in his Preface, where (ſpeaking of this Demonſtration together with the reſt) he ſayes, <hi>Non haec à me ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, ſed ab eo qui ex legibus Providentiae ſuae,</hi> &amp;c. are to be changed thus, (applying them to this particular) <hi>Non haec à me habes, ſed à Paulo Gul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deno, qui ante trigintaferè annos ea pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mò invenit, &amp; poſtea retractavit,</hi> &amp;c. After this relation Mr. <hi>White</hi> proceeds to confirme the ſaid Demonſtration and infringe the Retractation of <hi>Gul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> ſhewing his computation to be falſe, as he imagines: which done, he makes his <hi>Nota Quarta,</hi> or invective againſt <hi>Gulden</hi> in theſe words.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
                        <head>Nota Quarta.</head>
                        <p>Calculus itaque Guldenianus impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas eſt, &amp; qualem ab ipſo acceptari (neque enim vel talem ipſe inſtruxit)
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:61432:37"/> decebat, homine prorſus Amathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co, ut legenti ipſius ſcripta pronum eſt patere. Nam dum proportionem Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralis ad circulum ad ſtruere conare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, aſſumpſit ſine probatione propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem prorſus improbabilem, nempe, lineas intra aliam ductas eſſe minores illâ. Et ſi enim videatur de Inſcriptis velle loqui, tamen quas ipſe ſcribit ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil minus ſunt quans Inſcriptae, cum circum ſcriptam non accedant niſi al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tero duntaxat termino. Rurſus aequali temeritate vult Arcus circuli eſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionaliter medios inter arcus Spira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis aequalium angulorum. Sed (quod foediſſimum eſt) tantae vanitatis eſt, ut cum erraviſſe ſeſe putaverat, neque delendo tegere, neque candidè con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteri ſuſtinuerit, ſed excuſationes texe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re quaſi in ipſo errore egregiè ſe geſſerit, oſtentare pergat, Quae (utpote de ſumptae ex locis Logicis vel Rhetoricis) clarè docent hominem officij Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trici (quod hac reſpust) eſſe prorſus ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum, &amp; ex eo Semidoctorum genere, qui cum ex magnorum virorum ſcriptis egregia multa depeculati fuerint, ut ſua faeciant, additis quibuſdam levibus, juſti voluminis oftentatione ſe vulgò
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:61432:37"/> diſcentium oſtentant: &amp; (quod perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioſiſſimum eſt) mixtis incertis, ſacrum Scientiae nomen denigrant, ut abundè egit noſter Guldenus; Saltitationem telluris circa centrum, &amp; conſiſtentiam Centri in puncto imaginario, in Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metricum tractatum inferciens. H<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>c coactus ſum de homine caeteroqui ignoto prodere quia umbra Tomi illuſtris, per opinionem conſequam, officiebat veritati, quam ejuſdem ſtudioſis offerebam. Quantumvis operae pretium erat lecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem monitum redàere de exitiali hâc Sciolorum Sectâ, quae ſub profeſſione facultatis garriendi omnem certitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, tum è Scientiis, tum ex Fide Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianâ tollere molitur.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
                        <head>In Engliſh thus.</head>
                        <p>WHerefore <hi>Guldens</hi> calculation is unskilful, and ſuch as was fit to be received by him (for he made it not himſelf <note n="*" place="margin">But he there made another more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate.</note>) a man no way vers'd in Mathematick, as his Reader will eaſily perceive. For endeavouring to give the proportion of a Spiral to a Circle, he aſſumes without proof a propoſition wholly improbable, <hi>viz.</hi>
                           <pb n="66" facs="tcp:61432:38"/> that lines drawn within another line, are leſs then it. For though he ſeem to intend to ſpeak of lines inſcribed; yet thoſe he deſcribes are nothing leſs then ſuch, ſince they touch the circumſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed but with one end onely. In like manner with equal temerity he will have the Arches of a Circle to be mean proportionals between the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of a Spiral of equal <note n="*" place="margin">Both theſe are retra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by <hi>Gulden,</hi> prop. 4.</note> Angles. But that which above all is the moſt deteſtable, his vanity is ſo great, that when he thought he had erred, he could neither endure to ſuppreſs it, nor candidly to acknowledge it, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds framing excuſes, and brags, as if therein he had carried himſelf very gallantly. All which, being but flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes of Rhetorick, clearly ſhew him to be a man wholly ignorant of what belongs to Geometry; which uſes no ſuch Arts: and that he is one of thoſe petty Schollars, who having ſtollen divers excellent things out of other mens Writings, that they may make them ſeem their own, adde ſome few trivial matters, and then boaſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves amongſt their Schollars as the Authours of a great Volume: and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:61432:38"/> (which is moſt pernicious) by ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling many uncertainties, defile the Sacred Name of Science; as this <hi>Gulden</hi> hath done to the full, thruſting into a Geometricall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe the Dancing of the Earth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout its Center, and the Conſiſtency of the ſame Center in an Imaginary Point. Theſe things I was forced to publiſh of a man otherwiſe unknown to me, becauſe the ſhadow of ſo fair a Tome, through the opinion it had gain'd, hindered the light of that truth, which I propos'd to thoſe that ſought it. Nevertheleſs it was worth the labour, to admoniſh the Reader of this pernicious Sect of Scioliſts, who under profeſſion of the Faculty of Prating, endeavour to remove all certainty, as well from Sciences, as from Chriſtian Faith.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Hitherto we have heard, or rather ſeen Mr. <hi>Whites</hi> gall againſt this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, through whoſe ſides he unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily ſeems to endeavour the wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his whole Order, under the title of <hi>Exitialis Sciolorum Secta.</hi> Truly a man would wonder to ſee, how ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:61432:39"/> and compleatly Mr. <hi>White</hi> here acts the part of a malitious Detractor, ſeeking every way to defame his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary: for beſides what we have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready heard in the precedent Letter, he intimates him here to be ſo little verſed in the Mathematicks, as not to be able to make even the computation of a Polygone of twelve ſides: for ſpeaking (as we have heard) of ſuch a Calculation which he tearms unkilful, and calls it <hi>Guldens,</hi> (though he tells us withal, that <hi>Gulden</hi> made it not himſelf, but received it from another) he malitiouſly inſerts in a Parentheſis, <hi>Neque enim vel talem ipſe inſtruxit,</hi> thereby to inſinuate, that <hi>Gulden</hi> was unable to frame ſo trivial a Computa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as he (Mr. <hi>White</hi>) eſteemed this. Wherein yet he could not be ignorant of the great injury he did this Author; who having ſet down the ſaid Calcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of twelve ſides, acknowledging it to be none of his own, but ſent him from another, he examines and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves it in <hi>prop.</hi> I. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. Which done, he preſently in <hi>prop.</hi> 3. exhibites another of his own far more accurate, as conſiſting of a thouſand ſides, and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:61432:39"/> performed by a different way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, with laborious Tables expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the quantity of each particular ſide: thence alſo probably inferring that the proportion of the ſaid Spira<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to the half Circumference is as 1961 to 1818 <hi>proximè.</hi> Yet Mr. <hi>White</hi> would take no notice of this Computa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, although it were ſo near the place from whence he took that other of twelve ſides.</p>
            <p>But having attained his end in this he proceeds, finding a means to aſperſe him with a cenſure of abſolute igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the Mathematicks: where that the Reader may ſee Mr. <hi>Whites</hi> mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious way of proceeding, he muſt know that <hi>Gulden</hi> (as we ſhall preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hear in his own words) having (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the printing or publiſhing the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten mentioned Demonſtration of the Spiral) diſcovered by help of a Friend an errour therein, thought good not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding to print it, not as a true one, but as erroneus. This he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms in <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. and preſently <hi>c.</hi> 3. ſhews and refutes all the particular er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours committed in <hi>c.</hi> 2. to the end that others advertiſed of the errours
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:61432:40"/> committed in <hi>cap.</hi> 2. might beware of committing the like; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſciant</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſibi cavere à ſcopulis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now here Mr. <hi>White</hi> playes his game, and taking no notice at all of this, playes upon <hi>Gulden,</hi> as if he had affirmed the contents of <hi>cap.</hi> 2. to be really true; which, as I ſaid, <hi>Gulden</hi> did publiſh as abſolutely falſe: then which a more unworthy proceeding can hardly be imagined, as will now appear.</p>
            <p>For in the above named <hi>Nota Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> Mr. <hi>White</hi> terms him, <hi>Hominem prorſus Amathematicum,</hi> a man utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ignorant of the Mathematicks, in aſſuming (as he ſayes) without proof a Propoſition wholly improbable, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>Lines drawn within another are leſs then it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in this Mr. <hi>White</hi> extreamly wrongs the Authour, who onely ſets down <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Prop.</hi> 3. the ſaid Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as erroneous, which he took at firſt ſight to be true; and afterwards <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Prop.</hi> 1. at large declares the errour. Which had he not done, I dare boldly affirm, that all Mr. <hi>Whites</hi> Geometry would never have been able to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:61432:40"/> But by this proceeding Mr. <hi>White</hi> thinks to attain what he aimed at; <hi>viz.</hi> the depreſſing of <hi>Gulden,</hi> and the exalting of himſelf. For by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing <hi>Guldens</hi> refutation of the ſaid Propoſition, on the one ſide he would give the world to underſtand, that <hi>Gulden</hi> was not able to ſee and rectifie the errour: on the other he would gain to himſelf the opinion of a ſharp wit, and deep inſight into the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Geometry, in being able to detect what ſo great a Mathematician (as he reports in his <hi>Nota ſecunda</hi> that <hi>Gulden</hi> was eſteemed) could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive: whereas indeed if <hi>Gulden</hi> had not put it into Mr. <hi>Whites</hi> head, it had never been there. But to ſeek the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of a great Wit and profound Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematician, as alſo to purchaſe an eſteem to all his other Writings by ſuch Arts as theſe, is a thing moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of a Gentleman. And though ſuch Artifices may for a time, by ſome more affected to him then learned to diſcover them, be received with ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe; yet at laſt they will be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, as here they are, and inſtead of the hoped glory, bring nothing but
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:61432:41"/> ſhame to ſuch as uſe them.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, he accuſes <hi>Gulden</hi> of raſhneſs for affirming (as he ſayes) the circular Arches to be mean proportionalls be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Spiral Arches of equal An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles. Wherein he uſes the like artifice as before, by making <hi>Gulden</hi> aſſert even what he abſolutely denies. For this Aſſertion correſponds onely to what <hi>Gulden</hi> ſayes in the ſaid <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Prop.</hi> 8. where he delivers it as falſe, and after proves the falſity, <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>prop.</hi> 4, <hi>n.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>Thus much for Mr. <hi>VVhites</hi> invective againſt <hi>Gulden;</hi> let us now, if you pleaſe, hear <hi>Gulden</hi> ſpeak himſelf, and ſee whether there appear in his words that great vanity, ſtubbornneſs, want of candour, and ſuch oſtentation as Mr. <hi>VVhite</hi> reproaches him with: and thereupon frame a judgement of them both, accordingly. <hi>Gulden</hi> therefore in the Preface to the <hi>cap.</hi> 3. gives a full account of his retracting the Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Spirall: which is as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="extract">
               <body>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:61432:41"/>
                     <head>De Centro Gravitatis, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Pag.</hi> 58.</head>
                     <head type="sub">Examen eorum quae proxime praecedenti capite tradita ſunt.</head>
                     <p>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>cuſque ergo, amice Lector, novae haec, &amp; non minùs jucunda quàm pulchra, de lineis Spiralibus ſpeculatio non tam traxit, quàm tum equis quàm velis ſuaviſſimè nos provexit, nullum ſive in aequore ſive in montibus nobis ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes vel periculum apertum, vel inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias latentes. Nam regiâ nos incedere viâ ſcivimus potiùs, quàm arbitrati ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus; &amp; ſolùm intenti fuimus quâ ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione, Scopum videlicet noſtrum intuendo, nobis paulatim ſemitam ad indagandum Lineae Spiralis <hi>Gravitatis Centrum</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modè praepararemus. Occurrer at ſaepius quidem, dum haec tractaremus, non levis cogitatio; quae tamen ob certas rationes nos in caepto retardare minimè viſa eſt: nimirum ſi haec Spiralis Lineae dimenſio tam obvia, tam commoda, tamque ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata eſt, ut nos eam invenimus; tam fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilè etiam progreditur, támque firmis
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:61432:42"/> poteſt roborari Demonſtrationibus; cur cam non Magnus <hi>Archimedes,</hi> qui ea, quae alii de Lineâ Spirali propoſuerant, ipſe <hi>admirabili</hi> (ut cum <hi>Pappo</hi> loqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur) <hi>quâdam aggreſſione demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit;</hi> cur eam (inquam) Dimenſionem libro ſuo <hi>De Spiralibus</hi> non inſeruit? Sed facilè nobis ipſis reſponſum dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus: ipſum videlicet <hi>Archimedem</hi> plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra alia, quae tamen alii poſt ipſum tractâ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, velneglexiſſe, vel ſtudio ac volens praeteriiſſe; vel etiam jam ab ipſo tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctata, injuriâ temporum, intercidiſſe. Quemadmodum etiam fecit, cum ae Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum centro ageret gravitatis: omiſit enim Tractatum de centro Linearum. Et ſicut nos non abſterruit illa objectio ab indagatione <hi>Centri Gravitatis</hi> Linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, praeſertim Circularium; ſic &amp; hìc nobis ipſis fecimus animos novi aliquid <hi>circa Spirales</hi> inveniendi, quod vel ipſum <hi>Archimedem</hi> fugere, aut poſteros nos la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere potuerit.</p>
                     <p>Et noſtro quidem judicio rem tunc fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitèr &amp; incepimus, &amp; in eâdem ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnis etiam itineribus perreximus. Sed ecce dum hoc loco in medio quaſi eſſemus curſu, portumque etſi valdè procul ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huc poſitum, jam à longè tamen jam jam
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:61432:42"/> conſpiceremus, vela repentè &amp; erant contrahenda, &amp; ſecuritatis causâ ad le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genda littora prora convertenda. Incidi enim tunc primùm in Examen quoddam, per numeros inſtitutum, dimenſionis Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neae Spiralis; de quo antè quidem inau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diveram, ſed qualitèr ant quâ ratione dimenſio illa progrederetur, cum rectâne, an cum curvâ, aut purè circulari, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralis illa linea conferretur, omninò neſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ebam: tantum abeſt, ut ipſ<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> juſtam proportionem, à nobis inventam, inde redargui poſſe ſuſpicarer. Quare ex pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo illius aſpectu nequaquam ſum ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus; quippe qui meis fidebam Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrationibus, tam Geometricis quam Arithmeticis, quas irreprehenſibiles eſſe judicavi. Hoſtem tamen qualem qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem ſaepe audivi ſpernendum eſſe minimè: quippe qui, quando minimè putamus, vel obeſſe vel nocere poſſit.</p>
                     <p>Examinavi igitur examen illud; quo in labore mille potius ſperabam me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturum in calculo hujus examinis er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rores, quàm vel unicum in meis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventis. Sed contra quaſi accidit. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peri enim Lineam Spiralem primae Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culationis majorem eſſe Semiperipheriâ primi Circuli; &amp; tacitè victuſque ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:61432:43"/> dare debui. Quid facerem? Diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laremne? Tacerem? Mordicus mea, inſtar Circuli Quadratorum ſuprà no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatorum, defenderem? Et Archime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ipſum Euclidemque in jus vocarem, accuſarem, condemnarem? Nequaquam. Sed ſervandum mihi duxi id, quod ipſe <hi>Joſ. Scaliger</hi> ſibimet quidem ſervandum praeſcripſit; at minime ſervavit. Sic enim in Appendice ad ſua Cyclometrica habet. <q>Primum, aio, in omnibus Scientiis &amp; Artibus poſſe ſaepe tolerabilitèr pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri: in Mathematicis ne ſemel quidem debere. Nam ut ait quidam vetus Scriptor, <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> Ita<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> cum Mathematicus erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ſuum deprehenderit, primus occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare debet <hi>Me, Me, adſum, qui feci.</hi> Poſtquam autem per alium id cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verit, ſi non ſtatim Caſtigatori gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias agit, malè de homine; ſi non corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git, malè de Mathemetica meritus eſt.</q> Verum bonus ille <hi>Scaliger</hi> praecipuos erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſuos, atro &amp; rubro colore jam edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos, non ſolum non correxit; ſed &amp; majori inſcitiâ animique tumore pertina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citèr defendit. Concluſi ergo, in meis inventis alicubi peccatum eſſe. At ubi
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:61432:43"/> lateret anguis in herbâ, non it a facilè ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſtatim videre aut judicare potui. Quare Scripta mea amico in Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticis benè docto dedi perlegenda, ut an ea ſibi conſtarent animum diligentèr ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verteret, ſuumque mihi de iis judicium candidè aperiret, eundem rogavi.</p>
                     <p>Verùm enim verò dum ille differret lectitandi operam, ipſe errorem meum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peri, &amp; digito (quod aiunt) demonſtrare potui. In eo ſolùm haeſi, an totum illud Caput praecedens, cum principi meo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tento ac fini nihil tolleret; parum, etiamſi omnia vera eſſent, adferret, omittendum eſſet, totumque negotium menſurationis Lineae Spiralis diſſimulandum: an vero, prout jam ſcripta eſſent omnia, unà cum hoc Examine edenda. Occurrebant ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones plures &amp; variae, prò &amp; contrà: Vicerunt tamen illae, quae in bonum alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum laborem horum, partem ſaltem ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam, ipſis communicandum eſſe, caeteris praelatae ſunt, ſuasêrunt &amp; perſuaſerunt. Praeſertim cum non defint exempla Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum, qui &amp; cum laude ſuâ &amp; cum utilitate Lectorum idem factitârunt: qui ſi nullum alium hinc auferrent fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum, is ſaltem ſatis eſſe poſſet, quod in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniant cautionem, ut ſi curioſiùs ſive
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:61432:44"/> de Spiralibus, ſive de alijs inquirere ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lint, ſibi ſciant cavere &amp; à ſcopulis, &amp; ab alijs incommodis, in quae facillimè in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currere poſſent. Geometria profectò ipſa, ſecundum judicium <hi>Joſephi Scaligeri</hi> ſuprà <hi>cap.</hi> primo <hi>Propoſ.</hi> 4. <hi>num.</hi> 7. adductum, ſibi inprimis gratulabitur, quòd <hi>acceſſione</hi> ſaltem novorum aliquot <hi>Epichirematum</hi> locupletata ſit.</p>
                     <p>Primum igitur indicandum eſt, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter in cognitionem venimus inventa noſtra lubricae eſſe fidei; deinde, vbinam haereat error, oſtendendum: tum ſingulae propoſitiones examinandae, &amp; pro meritis approbandae vel reprobandae, &amp; ſiquidem id fieri commodè poterit, erroneae corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendae. Omiſimus autem plurima jam conſcripta, bonoque ordine ac methodo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſta; quae ſi rationibus ſuis ſolidè nixa fuiſſent, Lectori plurimùm oblectationi eſſe potuiſſent: cum verò vacillantia ea inventa fuerint, ne faſtidio potius eſſent, jure meritò ea praeterivimus. Non eſſet autem abs re cogitationem ſuſcipere, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſnam aut quae ſit illa flexuoſa linea, &amp; quâ arte illa compendioſe deſcribi poſſit, quae illas haberet proprietates, quas fruſtrà Spirali attribuimus. Id quod in aliud tempus, vel potius aliis faciendum reſervamus.</p>
                     <div n="1" xml:lang="lat" type="preposition">
                        <pb n="79" facs="tcp:61432:44"/>
                        <head>Propoſitio prima. Occaſionem Examinis hujus ac Dubitationis preſſius declarare.</head>
                        <p>F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſſe quendam, qui Dimenſionem Lineae Spiralis ante nos inſtituerit, memini me aliquando audiviſſe ex <hi>P. Hieronymo Kinig</hi> Societatis noſtrae Mathematico, &amp; olim in Ingolſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dianâ, Dilinganâ, ac Pragenſi Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demiis earundem Mathematicarum Diſciplinarum Profeſſore accuratiſſimo, mihi &amp; Romae &amp; alibi notiſſimo; imò eundem Lineam illam alicui alteri aequalem, ſine tamen ullâ Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione, pronunciaſſe; quod aſſertum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus ille Profeſſor examinaverit: cui vero Lineae illam adaequaverit, non ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lùm tunc ſcire, verum an aliquando id ſciverim planè meminiſſe non potni. Cum ergo verſarer in ſcriptione ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioris Capitis, venit in mentem Examen illud quod diximus, recordatione tamen ſatis confusâ. Exiſtens ergo Graecii in Stiriâ ſcribo Viennam, ubi Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticus
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:61432:45"/> ille manebat; &amp; ſiquid habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret his de rebus in Scripto, ad me mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teret rogavi: non quòd incertus eſſem de meis jam inventis &amp; ſcriptis, aut ullo modo de iiſdem dubitarem, ſed ut illud ipſum cum meis conferrem. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuit ipſe, &amp; ſequens ad me miſit, ſive Examen, ſive contra Aſſerta inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam &amp; reprobationem: quam cum examinaſſem, ut ſuprà diximus, eam veritati conſonam eſſe, manifeſtè de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendi. Sic autem ſe habebant illa.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="proposition">
                        <p n="2">2. <hi>Propoſitum ſit demonſtrare, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neam Spiralem majorem eſſe Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumferentiâ;</hi> Intellige Circuli pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mieam comprehendentis.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
                     <head>The ſame in Engliſh.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:61432:45"/> OF <hi>The Center of Gravity.</hi> Lib. 2. Cap. 3. Pag. 58.</head>
                     <p>THus far (Courteous Reader) had this new, and no leſs ſpecious then delightful ſpeculation on the ſubject of Spiral Lines rather ſwiftly advanced me, by Sea and Land as I may ſay, then ſlowly drawn me, who apprehended nothing either of appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent danger, or unexpected ſurprize. For indeed I rather knew, then ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d, that I travelled in the High Road; and looking ſtedfaſtly on my main deſign, I was wholly attentive to the means whereby to tread out a commodious Path for the Diſcovery of the <hi>Center of Gravity</hi> in the <hi>Spiral.</hi> True it is, while I was plodding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a ſerious reflection came often into my minde, which yet, for certain rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, was not ſufficient to retard my courſe, <hi>viz.</hi> That if this Dimenſion of the Spiral Line were ſo obvious, eaſie, and commodious a thing, as I found it
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:61432:46"/> to be; as alſo ſtrengthned with ſuch firm Demonſtrations, how came it to paſs that the great <hi>Archimedes,</hi> who (to ſpeak with <hi>Pappus</hi>) did with admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Dexterity demonſtrate thoſe Proprieties of the Spiral Line, which other men had onely hinted at; how came it, I ſay, to paſs that he did not inſert this Dimenſion into his Book of <hi>Spirals?</hi> But I eaſily anſwered my ſelf; to wit, that <hi>Archimedes</hi> had ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neglected or purpoſely omitted many other things, which have ſince his time been treated by others; or elſe it muſt be, that what he wrote thereof, hath periſhed by the injury of time. The like he did when he treated of the <hi>Center</hi> of <hi>Gravity</hi> in <hi>Plains;</hi> for he omitted the Tract of the <hi>Center of Lines.</hi> And as that objection deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me not from enquiring the Center of Gravity in Lines, eſpecially Circular ones, ſo here I encouraged my ſelf in hope to diſcover ſomething new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Spirals,</hi> which hitherto had eſcaped both <hi>Archimedes</hi> and all that had come after him.</p>
                     <p>And truly in my opinion I began the buſineſs happily enough, and had
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:61432:46"/> made a great progreſs therein; but on a ſudden when I was half way on my Voyage, and came within Kenning of the Port, I was fain to ſtrike Sail, and for ſecurity, to make directly towards the ſhore: for I then firſt lighted on a certain Examen of the Dimenſion of the Spiral Line, performed by numbers: whereof indeed, I had heard before, but could not tell how or which way that Dimenſion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded: or whether that Spiral were to be compared with a right Line or crooked, or a pure Circular Line. So far was I from ſuſpecting, that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act proportion I had already diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, could be diſproved thereby. So that I was nothing at all troubled at the firſt ſight of this <hi>Examen,</hi> as being very confident of my own Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, both Geometrical and Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metical, which I thought to be irrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible. Yet I had often heard, that an enemy, how mean ſoever he ſeems, ought not to be contemned; for when we leſt think of him, he may hap to ſtand in our way, if not do us a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief.</p>
                     <p>I took in hand therefore to examine
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:61432:47"/> that <hi>Examen,</hi> promiſing my ſelf to diſcover a thouſand errours in his Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, rather then one in my own Inventions. But it happened far otherwiſe; for I found that the <hi>Spiral Line</hi> of the firſt Revolution was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then the Semi-circumference of the firſt Circle: ſo that I ſaw I was fairly to ſubmit. <note n="*" place="margin">See how unjuſtly Mr. <hi>White</hi> charges this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of obſtinacy, for not confeſſing his errour.</note> For what ſhould I do? Should I diſſemble the matter? ſhould I hold my peace and conceal it? Or ſhould I, with thoſe Squarers of the Circle above-mentioned, obſtinately defend my own Aſſertion, though I knew it to be falſe? Should I dare to queſtion, accuſe, yea and condemn <hi>Archimedes</hi> and <hi>Euclide</hi> himſelf, to maintain my own opinion? By no means. I reſolved therefore to obſerve the Rule, which <hi>Joſeph Scaliger</hi> once preſcribed to himſelf, but never ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. It is in the <hi>Appendix</hi> to his <hi>Cyclometriques;</hi> where he thus ſpeaks. <q>
                           <hi>I grant,</hi> ſaith he, that in all other Arts and Sciences, errour may be tollerably committed <hi>oftentimes:</hi> but in the Mathematiques it ought not <hi>ſo much as once.</hi> For as an old Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, &amp;c. All things digeſted
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:61432:47"/> by Art ought to have an unreprove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able evidence. So that a Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matician obſerving his own errour, ought before all others to cry out, <hi>'Tis I, 'tis I, here I am that did it.</hi> But if he comes to know it by means of ſome other perſon, unleſs he preſently gives thanks to his Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectour, he is ill-deſerving towards the man; but if he do not preſently amend his errour, he wrongs the Science it ſelf.</q> Yet this honeſt <hi>Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liger</hi> was ſo far from correcting his own over-ſights, publiſhed both in black and red, that with greater igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and animoſity he ſtill obſtinately defended them. I concluded therefore with my ſelf, that ſomething was amiſs in my Deductions. But where this Snake (the errour) lay, I could neither ſo eaſily nor ſo preſently perceive. Wherefore I gave theſe my Writings to a Friend well skilled in the Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks to read them over; entreating him to conſider as attentively as he could, whether they were conſiſtent or not; and that he would impart his judgement of them to me with all candour and clearneſs.</p>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:61432:48"/>
                     <p> But to tell you the plain truth, while my Friend deferred ſomewhat the pains of reading my Writings, I in the mean time diſcovered the errour my ſelf, and was able (as the Proverb ſaith) to point it out with my finger. Onely I could not well reſolve, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ſhould now wholly lay aſide the foregoing Chapter, (ſeeing that to do ſo would not be any prejudice to my principal intent, as on the other ſide it would not have added much to it, though every thing therein had proved true) and ſo diſſemble the whole matter concering the meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the <hi>Spiral Line;</hi> or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhould publiſh whatſoever I had written on that Subject, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with this <hi>Examen.</hi> Many and various Reaſons occurred to me <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con:</hi> but at laſt thoſe prevailed, which for the <note n="*" place="margin">See if this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors not expunging his errour proceeded out of pride, as he is accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> good of others incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me to think that ſome part at leaſt even of thoſe my Labours, was not to be denied to the publick. Eſpecially ſeeing there wanted not the examples of Authours, who to their own praiſe, and the benefit of their Readers have done the like; who though they ſhould
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:61432:48"/> happen to reap no other profit by it, yet were this alone ſufficient, that they have here a <hi>Caveat</hi> given them, that in caſe they ſhould themſelves deſire to ſearch more curiouſly into this Subject of <hi>Spiral Lines,</hi> or any other of like nature, they ſhould proceed warily and adviſedly in the <note n="†" place="margin">Where is now that great vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Maſter <hi>White</hi> would pin upon this Authour?</note>buſineſs, for the avoiding of thoſe rocks of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences and errour, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they will moſt eaſily run upon. And laſtly, that <hi>Geometry</hi> it ſelf, even according to the judgement of the ſame <hi>Joſeph Scaliger,</hi> (cap. 1. prop. 4. num. 7.) <hi>ſhould rejoyce, being enriched thereby with the Addition of ſome New Endeavours.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The firſt thing therefore here to be done is to declare, how I came to know that my Inventions were but doubtful and uncertain; next to ſhew where the errour lyes: and laſtly to examine all the ſeverall Propoſitions, with approbation or rejection of them according to their merits; yea (where it may conveniently be done) by rectifying and correcting thoſe which are erroneous. Yet many things I have omitted, though already written,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:61432:49"/> and digeſted by me into due order and method; which had they been built upon good and ſolid grounds, would have given great delight to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. But finding them looſe and ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, (to avoid offence) I have juſtly laid them aſide. However, it might (perhaps) be matter not unworthy our conſideration, to think what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Bending Line that is, (and alſo how it may be compendiouſly drawn, and deſcribed) which might be found to have all thoſe properties, which in the <hi>Spiral Line</hi> we have hitherto but vainly ſought. But that's a thing I muſt defer to ſome other time, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leave to other perſons to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form.</p>
                     <div n="1" type="preposition">
                        <head>The Firſt Propoſition. More particularly to declare the occaſion of this following <hi>Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and of Doubting.</head>
                        <p>THat there was one, who before me had attempted the meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the <hi>Spiral Line,</hi> I remember well to have heard long ſince from the mouth of <hi>Father Hierome Kinig,</hi> a
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:61432:49"/> Mathematician of our Society, and formerly a moſt accurate profeſſour of thoſe Sciences in the Univerſities of <hi>Ingolſtad, Dilingen,</hi> and <hi>Prague;</hi> whom I knew very well both at <hi>Rome</hi> and elſewhere; yea, that the aboveſaid perſon had affirmed (but without any Demonſtration given) that the ſaid <hi>Spiral Line</hi> was exactly equal to ſome other Line: which Aſſertion of his the ſaid profeſſor did alſo examine. But to what Line he made the <hi>Spiral</hi> to be equal, I cannot poſſibly call to minde, whether I did either then, or any other time know it in all my life. Whileſt therefore I was writing the precedent Chapter, I hapned to think on the afore mentioned <hi>Examen;</hi> yet remembring it but confuſedly, and in groſs. Whereupon being at <hi>Gratz</hi> in <hi>Stiria,</hi> I wrote to <hi>Vienna</hi> where the ſaid Mathematician then was, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated him, that if he had any thing of this Subject, he would ſend it in writing to me; not that I was then any way jealous of my ſelf, or did in the leaſt meaſure doubt of my own writings and diſcoveries; but onely that I might communicate what I had
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:61432:50"/> written, with thoſe of my own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. He forthwith yielded to my requeſt, and ſent me this following <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amen,</hi> or rather refutation of the things I had aſſerted; which having my ſelf examined, (as I ſaid before) I manifeſtly found it agreeable to truth. Now that which he wrote was as followeth.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="proposition">
                        <p n="2">2. The ſecond Propoſition may be to ſhew, that the <hi>Spiral Line</hi> is greater then the Semi circumference to wit, the Semi-circumference of the firſt Circle that contains it.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Though I had here ended my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional Vindication of a worthy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematician by the name of <hi>Gulden,</hi> becauſe I found him ſo written by the Author of the precedent Letter, as following Mr. <hi>White,</hi> who names him <hi>Paulus Guldenus;</hi> yet I thought it not amiſs to advertiſe the Reader be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I took Pen from Paper, that his Adverſary could not be ignorant that he calls himſelf <hi>Paulus Guldinus</hi> in his own printed works, not <hi>Guldenus.</hi> Whereby one may probably conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, that this was a meer affected mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:61432:50"/> in Mr. <hi>White,</hi> to confirm his Reader in the belief of that incredible ſtory he delivers, that he had never ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeen, nor heard of this Authors Work, till his own was ready for the Preſs.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
